Guide to the Irma D'Ascenzo Papers, 1944-1991 AIS.2018.04
ULS Archives & Special Collections
Irma D'Ascenzo Papers
1944-1991
1956-1970
ULS Archives & Special Collections
D'Ascenzo, Irma
AIS.2018.04
5 Linear Feet (6 manuscript boxes, 4 oversize folders)
The Irma D'Ascenzo Papers document the civic and political career of Pittsburgh City Councilwoman Irma D'Ascenzo between 1944-1991.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Joan M. McDonald in 2018.
Biography
Irma Manella D'Ascenzo was a politician and civic leader who served as the first female Pittsburgh City Council member between 1956-1970.
Born to an Italian-American family in Pittsburgh's Hazelwood neighborhood in 1905, D'Ascenzo attended Cathedral High School and graduated from Duff's Business College along with studying Business Administration at University of Pittsburgh. After college, she worked as Secretary and Chief Examiner of the Civil Service Commission of the City of Pittsburgh. Inspired by interests in civic affairs, government and politics, D'Ascenzo remained active in the Democratic Party for her entire career. Her political engagements included service in the Speaker's Bureau of the Allegheny County Democratic Committee along with being an Executive Board Member of the Democratic Women's Guild where she would eventually become Vice President. Other political posts included a term as Legislative Chairman for the Pennsylvania Federation of Democratic Women, delegate or alternate delegate to the Democratic National Conventions from 1944 to 1968 and membership in the Democratic Nationality Committee of Allegheny County.
In 1956, D'Ascenzo was appointed by Mayor David L. Lawrence to serve as a member of the City Council of Pittsburgh, becoming the first women to hold such a position. Her enterprise and quick grasp of municipal problems won the admiration of both citizens and colleagues and earned her election for a two-year term in 1957 followed by a full four-year term in 1959. During her time as council member, D'Ascenzo served as chair of the Parks, Recreation and Library Committee, overseeing funding and zoning projects in the city and working to improve and expand recreational facilities for youths city-wide. She also played an aggressive role in providing new and expanded facilities for senior citizens, leading to her appointment as a delegate to the President's White House Conference on the Aging.
Among D'Ascenzo's numerous civic activities was her work as founder and President of the Consolata Mission Women's Auxiliary, which helped young Italian priests prepare for missionary work in Africa through a graduate degree program at Duquesne University. During World War II, she was staff assistant to for the Red Cross Foreign Inquiry Department, Executive Secretary for the Western Pennsylvania Polio drives and Vice-Chairman of the Western Pennsylvania Committee for the Boy's Towns of Italy, for which she was awarded the Star of Solidarity from the Republic of Italy. Other civic engagements included executive service in the Catholic Laymen's Association, Gumbert School for Girls, Governor's Committee on Children and Youth, Allegheny County Smoke Control Advisory Committee, Allegheny County Housing Authority and Redevelopment Authority and Carnegie Museum and Libraries. In 1968, D'Ascenzo became the first female president of the National Council of the University of Pittsburgh, which oversees the Cathedral of Learning's Nationality Rooms. The next year, she became the first acting female council president, temporarily filling in for the regular president when he became hospitalized.
D'Ascenzo died suddenly after a car accident on March 1, 1970. She was married to Frank D'Ascenzo (1901-1967), a construction supervisor for the Allegheny County Works Department. They had three children, John J. D'Ascenzo (1927-2005), who served as Executive Vice President of Winkleman's department store in Detroit, Michigan, Rosemary D'Ascenzo (1925-), who served as Chairwoman of the City Planning Commission, and Frances J. D'Ascenzo (1924-1924).
Arrangement
The Irma D'Ascenzo Papers are organized in six series:
Series I. Pittsburgh City Council (1956-1970)
Series II. Political Organizations (1944-1970)
Series III. Civic and Professional Organizations (1945-1971)
Series IV. Personal (1940s-1970s)
Series V. Rosemary D'Ascenzo (1970-1991)
Series VI. Photographs (1950s-1960s)
Scope and Content Notes
The Irma D'Ascenzo Papers document the political career of Irma D'Ascenzo, a Pittsburgh City Councilwoman between 1956 and 1970 as well as her daughter Rosemary D'Ascenzo, who served on the Pittsburgh City Planning Commission between 1965 and 1991. The papers contain correspondence, newsclippings, photographs and subject files related to D'Ascenzo's political career and involvement in the Democratic Party as well her work in several major civic and professional organizations such as the Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh and Boys Town of Italy.
Allegheny County (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Elections -- Pennsylvania -- Allegheny County; Civics; Women -- Pennsylvania -- Political activity; Women civic leaders -– Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Politics and government; Pittsburgh (Pa.) -- Officials and employees; Italian American women -- Political activity -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; Italian American women -- Pennsylvania -- Pittsburgh; D'Ascenzo, Rosemary; D'Ascenzo, Irma; Pittsburgh (Pa.). City Council; Order Italian Sons and Daughters of America; Democratic Party (Pa.); Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh; WQED (Television station: Pittsburgh, Pa.)
- Pittsburgh City Council, 1956-1970; I.
  Scope and Content Notes
  Series I. City Council contains memos, correspondence, newsclippings, campaign materials and subject files related to D'Ascenzo's service as City Councilwoman between 1956 and 1970.
  - Air Travel Card (North America), no date (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Allegheny County Elected Officials List, no date (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographies, c.1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Biographies, c.1950s-1960s (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Business and Employee Identification Cards, c.1950s (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Campaign Cards, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Campaign Matchbook, no date (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Civic Club of Allegheny, County Voter Directory, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Council Memos and Correspondence, 1956-1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Council Memos and Correspondence, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Democratic Party Election Tickets, 1957-1963 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Election Advertisement, no date (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Election Congratulation Letters, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Election Congratulation Letters, 1957-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Frank D'Ascenzo, Council Motion for Silent Prayer, May 8, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - General Election Listing, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Jim Drake "Duck Letter", no date (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Municipal Record: Proceedings of the City Council of Pittsburgh, 1956-1969 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - News Clippings, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - News Clippings, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - News Clippings, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - News Clippings, 1955-1970 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Publicity File, 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Quotation Booklet, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Testimonial Luncheon Tickets, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Thank You Letter, no date (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - University of Pittsburgh Archives Letter and Brochure, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - WQED, 1962-1969 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - City Council Election Certificate, December, 1963 (Box 3, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 1)
  - City of Pittsburgh and 3rd Class City Election Districts Vote Listings, no date (Box 3, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 1)
  - Irma D'Ascenzo Office Nameplate, no date (Box 3, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 1)
  - Ruggero J. Aldisert Court of Common Pleas Induction Speech, December 29, 1969 (Box 3, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 1)
- Political Organizations, 1944-1970; II.
  Series II. Political Organizations contains correspondence, information files and newsclippings related to D'Ascenzos involvement in regional and national affiliates of the Democratic Party including the Allegheny County Democratic Committee, Pennsylvania Democratic Committee and Democratic National Committee.
  - "At the Sound of the Gavel" Booklet, no date (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Allegheny County Democratic Committee, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Allegheny County Democratic Committee, 1960-1967 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Conference Schedule, June 9, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Democratic Candidates Reception and Tea Invitation, 1963 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Democratic National Committee, 1963-1964 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Department of Defense "Our Flag" Booklet, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Italian-American Democratic Committee, Election Newsletter, November, 1957 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - John F. Kennedy Presidential Inauguration, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Lyndon Baines Johnson Presidential Inauguration, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Mayor Joseph M. Barr "Keep the Barr Team" Brochure, ca.1966 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Mayor Pete Flaherty Inauguration Schedule, January 5, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - News Clippings, 1948-1968 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Pennsylvania Democratic Committee, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Pennsylvania Federation of Democratic Women, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Pennsylvania League of Cities, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - White House Conference on Aging, ca.1961 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Democratic National Convention, Alternate Delegate Certificate, April, 1944 (Box 4, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 2)
  - Democratic National Convention Delegate at Large, January 1964 (Box 4, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 2)
  - Democratic National Convention Alternate Delegate at Large, May 1968 (Box 4, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 2)
  - Voter's Guide to the Municipal Primary Election, May 16, 1967 (Box 4, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 2)
- Civic and Professional Organizations, 1945-1971; III.
  Series III. Civic and Professional Organizations contains correspondence, memos, brochures and certificates related to D'Ascenzo's involvement in several regional and national organizations including the Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh and Boys Town of Italy.
  - "Pittsburgh Women: A Bicentennial Tribute, 1758-1958" (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - "The Authorities and the University" Brochure, c.1953 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - American National Red Cross Certificate, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - American Wind Symphony Orchestra Board Listings, no date (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Amita Inc. Scholarship Awards Ceremony, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Bishop Wright, Pittsburgh Catholic Diocese, Installation Ceremony, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Boys Town of Italy, Women's Division Dinner and Reception for Princess Gabriella Pacelli Program, 1951 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Carnegie Institute and Library Board of Trustees List, no date (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, 70th Anniversary Program, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, 75th Anniversary Committee List, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, Anniversary Committee Thank You Letter, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Carnegie Library of Pittsburgh, Program Planning Resources Book, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Catholic School Board Diocese of Pittsburgh Letter, no date (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Consolata Women's Auxiliary Annual Benefit Program, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Consul General of Italy, 1951-1956 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Fifteenth Ward Chamber of Commerce Certificate of Award, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - First Lady of the Day Award Certificate, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Gumbert Industrial School for Girls Speech, 1945 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - International Poetry Forum, 1970-1971 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Italian Club Women Testimonial Luncheon Announcement, 1959 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Children's Hospital Gift Speech, August 1954 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Golden Jubilee Program, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Honorary Reception Invitation, 1956 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America, National Convention Presidential Speech Synopsis, 1954 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Public Relations Letter, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - John Birch Society Note, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - John Simon Guggenheim Memorial Foundation Candidate for Fellowship Application, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Kiwanis Club of Brookline Certificate, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Newsclippings, 1954-1970 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Newsclippings, 1954-1970 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Newsclippings, 1954-1970 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Office of Cultural and Educational Exchange Scholarships List (Irma D'Ascenzo Memorial Award), 1971 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Pittsburgh Police Fort Pitt Lodge News, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Saturnia Farewell Dinner Programs, September 12, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - St. Francis Hospital of Pittsburgh, Certificate of Gratitude, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - St. Francis Hospital of Pittsburgh, Open House Brochure, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - St. Joseph's Protectory Centenary Commemoration, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - St. Mary School Postcard, 1961 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - St. Paul's Cathedral Newsletter, March 8, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - St. Stephen Church Newsletter, October 31, 1965 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Superintendent of Catholic Schools Memo, no date (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Testimonial Luncheon Committee Minutes, 1959 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - The Christophers "Christopher Notes", 1961 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Tour Itineraries, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - University of Pittsburgh Nationality Council Chairman's Message, May 1968 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Boys Town of Italy, Honorary Citizen Certificate, no date (Box 5, Drawer 32-3, Folder 3)
  - Boys Town of Italy, Honorary Citizen Certificate, no date (Box 5, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 3)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America, Award of Honor Certificate, August 1956 (Box 5, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 3)
  - President of the Republic of Italy Star of Solidarity Certificate, March 1951 (Box 5, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 3)
- Personal, ca. 1940s-1970; IV.
  Series IV. Personal contains a World War II-era ration booklet cover, Christmas cards and correspondence, memorials and newsclippings related to the deaths of Frank and Irma D'Ascenzo.
  - Christmas Cards, ca. 1960s (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Frank D'Ascenzo, Death Correspondence, 1967 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Irma D'Ascenzo, Death Memorials and Correspondence, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Irma D'Ascenzo, Death Memorials and Correspondence, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Irma D'Ascenzo, Funeral Guest Book, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Newsclippings, 1970 (Box 5, Folder 21)
- Rosemary D'Ascenzo, 1970-1991; V.
  Series V. Rosemary D'Ascenzo contains correspondence, memos and newsclippings related to Rosemary D'Ascenzo's service as a member of the Pittsburgh City Planning Commission.
  - City Planning Commission, Memos and Correspondence, 1970-1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - City Planning Commission, Service Certificate, no date (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Newsclippings, 1973-1989 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Newsclippings, 1973-1989 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Newsclippings, 1973-1989 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Newsclippings, 1973-1989 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Newsclippings, 1973-1989 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - St. Paul Cathedral Newsletters, September 23, October 21 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Photographs, ca. 1950s-1960s; VI.
  Series IV. Photographs contains photographs of D'Ascenzo at various gatherings and events related to her political career and involvement in several civic and professional organizations.
  - Beechview Branch of the Carnegie Library Ribbon Cutting and Opening, 1967 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Boys Town of Italy Events, 1955 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Chatham Center Site Photograph, no date (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Christopher Columbus Monument Ceremony (Schenley Park), no date (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - David L. Lawrence Portrait, no date (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Democratic Party Events, no date (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Downtown Pittsburgh, no date (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Holiday House (Monroeville, PA) Event, no date (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - Hubert Humphrey Portrait, no date (Box 6, Folder 17)
  - Italian Sons and Daughters of America Events, 1952-1966 (Box 6, Folder 18)
  - Mt. St. Anne, Ebensburg Group Photo, August 4, 1962 (Box 6, Folder 19)
  - Pittsburgh Aqua Zoo Opening, no date (Box 6, Folder 20)
  - Pittsburgh City Council, 1956 (Box 6, Folder 21)
  - Pope Paul VI, no date (Box 6, Folder 22)
  - Portraits, undated (Box 6, Folder 23)
  - Princess Pacelli Pittsburgh Visit, December 1951 (Box 6, Folder 24)
  - Rosemary D'Asenzo Swearing In Ceremony, 1970 (Box 6, Folder 25)
  - Saturnia Dinner, August 1958 (Box 6, Folder 26)
  - Senator John Pastore Presidential Campaign Opening, 1964 (Box 6, Folder 27)
  - Speaking Photos, no date (Box 6, Folder 28)
  - Testimonial Dinner Honoring Irma D'Ascenzo, October 25, 1959 (Box 6, Folder 29)
  - Unidentified Event Photographs, no date (Box 6, Folder 30)
  - Unidentified Ribbon Cutting Ceremony, no date (Box 6, Folder 31)
  - Unidentified Small Group Photographs, no date (Box 6, Folder 32)
  - Irma D'Ascenzo Portrait, no date (Box 6, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 4)
  - Pittsburgh City Council Photo (Labeled), 1959 (Box 6, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 4)
  - Pittsburgh City Council Photo (Unlabeled), 1959 (Box 6, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 4)
  - Pittsburgh City Council Photo (Unlabeled), 1959 (Box 6, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 4)
  - Pittsburgh City Council Photo (Unlabeled), no date (Box 6, Drawer 32-3, Oversize 4)